Mostofa Rafid Uddin

Summary

- PhD candidate at Carnegie Mellon University School of Computer Science.
- Fellow of Center for Machine Learning in Health Research 2023.
- Experienced Researcher in Machine Learning (ML) and Computer Vision (CV) with 1st authored paper at CVPR.
- Highly proficient in Deep Learning with Pytorch and data structure and algorithms.
- Experienced Tutor/TA of Machine Learning with excellent communication and presentation skills.

Research Interests & Expertise

Research Topics of Interest: *High Expertise:* Unsupervised, Self-supervised Representation Learning, Contrastive Learning, 3D Computer Vision, Object detection and Segmentation, Structural Bioinformatics.

<u>Moderate Expertise:</u> Deep Generative Models, Probabilistic Graphical Models, Domain adaptation, Domain Generalization, Vision Foundation Models, Geometric Learning.

Datasets of expertise: Scene-centric images, 3D tomographic images, Microscopy images, 3D data with various representations, Biological Sequence Data.

Education

2021- Present	Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D), School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA Advisor: Min Xu Distinctions: CMLH Fellowship for Digital Health 2023, Outstanding Research Accomplishment Award 2024.
2021- 2024	Master of Science (M.Sc.), Computational Biology- Advanced Study, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA Relevant Coursework: Machine Learning (Ph.D.) level, Computer Vision, Probabilistic Graphical Models.
2014 -2018	Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET), Dhaka, Bangladesh. Academic distinctions: Deans list awards, University merit scholarships. Relevant Coursework: Computer Graphics, Object-oriented Programming, Structured Programming, Pattern Recognition, Digital Image Processing.

Selected Research Publications

A few representative publications are mentioned here. For a full and up-to-date list, please visit my google scholar link.

- Mostofa Rafid Uddin, Gregory Howe, and Min Xu. Harmony: A Generic Unsupervised Approach for Disentangling Semantic Content from Parameterized Transformations. *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, 2022, pp. 20646-20655. (H5-index: 356). [paper link] [news link]. Skills: Unsupervised Learning, Representation Learning, Deep Generative Models, Bio-image Analyses.
 - In many real-life image analyses, particularly biomedical research domains, objects in the images undergo several parameterized transformations.
 - I developed an unsupervised method to disentangle the transformations from image contents and demonstrate that it significantly facilitates many downstream tasks.
- Mostofa Rafid Uddin, Sazan Mahbub, M Saifur Rahman, and Md Shamsuzzoha Bayzid. SAINT: Self-Attention Augmented Inception-Inside-Inception Network Improves Protein Secondary Structure Prediction. *Bioinformatics*, 2020 Nov 1; 36(17):4599-608. (H5-index: 136, Impact Factor: 6.937) [paper link]. Skills: Neural Machine

Translation, Structural Bioinformatics, Dense Prediction.

- Predicting 8-state (Q8) secondary structure from amino acid sequences of protein is an important but challenging problem.
- Developed a self-attention augmented inception-inside-inception network that improves state-of-the-art protein secondary structure prediction and recovers insights of protein folding through interpretable attention features

Technical Skills

Languages: Python, Java, C, C++. **HPC Computing:** AMD Cluster, TMUX, Oracle Cloud, AWS. **Frameworks:** Pytorch, Detectron, Tensorflow, OpenCV, Numpy, Scipy, Scikit-learn.

Work Experience

2021 - Present	Graduate Research Assistant, Computational Biology Department, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, PA, USA
2022	Graduate Teaching Assistant, Computational Biology Department, Spring 2022 CMU 02-620: Machine Learning for Scientists Fall 2022 CMU 02-740: Bioimage Informatics
2019- 2020	Lecturer, Department of Computer Science and Engineering, East West University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

Grants, Awards, & Services

- Center for Machine Learning and Health (CMLH) fellowship in Digital Health, 2023 CMLH fellowships, around 100,000 USD worth, are awarded each year to several (around 10) outstanding digital health-related research proposals by CMU PhD students. I received the award in 2023. [link] Skills: Grant Writing, Independent Research.
- Outstanding Research Accomplishment Award This award is given each year to one CMU PhD student from the Computational Biology Department who has contributed significant research during his time in the PhD program. Skills: Independent Research.
- Regularly serve as a reviewer in top AI and vision conferences such as CVPR, ICCV, ECCV, NeurIPS, AAAI, WACV, etc.
- Worked as a mentor in CMU AI Mentoring Program, where I mentor CMU undergraduate students coming from underrepresented communities interested in AI research
- Gave research talk on IEEE Applied Imagery Pattern Recognition (AIPR) Workshop (virtual), October 2021, Washington, DC, US. [link]
- Won best poster award at 3rd International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS 2017). Poster Title: Archiving Medical Records in DNA Sequence[pdf] Skills: Precision Health, Electronic Health Records

Mini-Research Projects

- ♦ Pytorch Implemented Local Energy Minimizer Implemented the local energy minimizer module of OpenMM software by modifying pytorch autograd mechanics. [qithub]
- ♦ Edge prediction: Predicting Edge in Academic Citation Networks Predicted how likely an academic article is to cite another particular article using an intelligent and novel feature engineering pipeline that could generate highly accurate predictions with relatively simpler models. [github]
- \Diamond Predicting age from lung single cell data Applied multiple feature extraction models and classifiers to predict biological age from scRNA-seq data of multiple control patients. [github]
- ♦ Onubadok: Bangla to English Machine Translation Using Seq2Seq Model with Attention Mechanism. In this project on Neural Machine Translation(NMT), I observed that using Bahdanau's attention with a vanilla encoder-decoder model improves BLEU score for Bangla to English translation. [github]